Good afternoon everybody. Today's דף *daf* is כ"ח *Kaf-Chet*, 28, and we
are picking up at the bottom of כ"ז עמוד ב' *Kaf-Zayin Amud
Bet*, and we're dealing with the משנה mishna *Mishna* dealt with the
case about אין שבועה חלה על שבועה ein shvua chal al shvua.
*ein shvua chala al shvua*. I won't eat, I won't eat, I
won't eat. The second one that's to forbid something that the first
one didn't, it takes effect, but a redundant doesn't take effect. Okay,
and then, and then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* spoke about the second
one sort of hovering, so if you manage to retroactively remove the
first one through שאלה she'ilah לחכם *sheila l'chacham*, the second one would
take effect. So we pick up at the bottom of כ"ז עמוד
ב' *Kaf-Zayin Amud Bet*. אמר רבא Amar Rava. *Amar Rava*, six lines
from the bottom. נשבע על הכיכר ואכלה *Nishba al hakikar v'achala*. So
first we're going to deal with the case about being שאלה she'ilah.
לחכם *shael l'chacham*. How late in the game can you go ahead
and ask the חכם chacham *chacham* to retroactively, you know, sort of
negate the, void the שבועה shavua *shvua*? So if somebody took a
נדר neder. *neder* regarding a loaf of bread and he ate it,
אם שייר הימנו כזית kezayis, *im shiyer heimenu kezayit*, נשאל עליה *nishal
aleha*. If there was a כזית kezayis. *kezayit* left, then it's still
like his שבועה shavua *shvua* is still present, there's still relevance to
his שבועה shavua *shvua*, and he can go to a חכם Chacham
*chacham* and say, I need you to get me out of this
שבועה shavua *shvua*. Okay, but notice, he might have already transgressed eating
the first few כזיתים kezaysim *kezeisim*, we'll discuss that in a minute.
But as long as there's something that's still remaining that's in effect,
he can go and ask. אכלה
כולה *Achala kula*, ate all of it, אין נשאל עליה *ein nishal
aleha*. Then it's too late. What's past is past. You can't have
him undermine something that has no current relevance. You might have transgressed
in the past, but it has no current relevance. So אמר ליה
Amar lei, רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי *Amar lei Rav Acha
brei d'Rava l'Rav Ashi*. So רב אחא *Rav Acha* the son of
רבא Rava *Rava* said to רב אשי Rav Ashi *Rav Ashi*. היכי
דמי *Heichi dami*? Now listen, we have to understand what exactly was
your שבועה shavua *shvua* to appreciate what רבא Rava *Rava* is saying.
אי דאמר שלא אוכל *Ei d'amar
shelo ochel*. If he says I won't eat from this. So we
said I won't eat means without אוכלנה *ochlena*, eat it, which means
the whole thing. Eat means you transgress even a כזית kezayis, *kezayit*.
So מכזית קמיה קמא עבד ליה איסורא *m'kezayit kamei kama avad lei
issura*. So he ate everything except a כזית kezayis? *kezayit*. So the
first three, you know, 90%
of it, he violated his שבועה shavuah *shvua* ten
times. Okay, so therefore, isn't that too late? Once you violate your
שבועה shavuah, *shvua*, it might be that there's still a כזית kezayis.
*kezayit* left that your שבועה shavuah. *shvua* is relevant for, but can
you really undo your שבועה shavuah *shvua* after you violated it? אי
דאמר שלא אוכלנה shelo ochlena, *Ei d'amar shelo ochelena*, and if he
said I won't eat it, which means its
entirety. מאי כזית kezayis *Mai kezayit*? Why is it only if there's
a כזית kezayis. *kezayit* left? אפילו כל שהוא נמי *afilu kol shehu
nami*, even if there's a tiny bit left, then he should still
be allowed to undo it, because presumably the פשט peshat. *pshat* of
this גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* disagree, that the פשט p'shat
*pshat* of this גמרא Gemara *Gemara* seems to be if you said
I won't eat it, you don't transgress until you eat every last
bit. And if you leave over even less than a כזית kezayis.
*kezayit*, you still haven't transgressed. So as long as he still hasn't
transgressed, why can't he? So according to רב אשי Rav Ashi. *Rav
Ashi*, רב אשי Rav Ashi *Rav Ashi* would say, look, the one
determining factor should be if you already transgressed, then it's too late.
We're not going to do a היתר נדרים heter nedarim. *heter nedarim*
to retroactively get you out of having violated. Okay, even if there's
still some current relevance left, there's still the rest of the loaf.
And if you haven't transgressed, then why can't we do a היתר
heter. נדרים nedarim *heter nedarim* till the very last minute? Why should
it matter כזית kezayis. *kezayit* or not a כזית kezayis *kezayit*? Very
reasonable question. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* answers. דף
כ"ח עמוד א' *Daf Kaf-Chet Amud Aleph*. איבעית אימא שלא אוכל *Iba'it
eima shelo ochel*, איבעית אימא שלא אוכלנה *iba'it eima shelo ochelena*. You
know what? רבא Rava. *Rava*'s statement is theoretically possible, we don't know
what רבא Rava. *Rava* meant, but it's possible to explain it either
in the context of I won't eat, where every כזית kezayis *kezayit*
is a transgression, or in the context of I won't eat it,
where only the whole loaf is a transgression. איבעית אימא שלא אוכל
*Iba'it eima shelo ochel*. Here's how it would work in the case
of שלא אוכל *shelo ochel*, where every כזית kezayis *kezayit* would be
a transgression. So yes, it's true, you already transgressed ten times. But
there's one כזית kezayis *kezayit* left. And you could do a שאילה
sheila, *sheila*, it is acceptable to ask a חכם Chacham *chacham* to
get you out of your שבועה shvua *shvua* in order to allow
you to eat this remaining כזית kezayis? *kezayit*. He's not just getting
you out of your שבועה shvua *shvua* in order to fix the
sin you already did. Presumably that, interesting question by the way, whether
this means is this לכתחילה l'chatchila? *l'chatchila* or בדיעבד *b'di'eved*, right? If
the חכם Chacham. *chacham* went ahead with it after you violated, would
it still work? But certainly לכתחילה *l'chatchila* we are not, this process
of היתר heter נדרים *heter nedarim* is to deal with the future,
allowing you to act more freely going forward. Okay, it is not
a way of retroactively fixing a past sin. That's not what this
institution is about. Whether בדיעבד *b'di'eved* it would work for that is
not clear. Okay, so he says, yes, in the scenario where there's
still a כזית kezayis *kezayit* left, then this היתר heter נדרים *heter
nedarim* will help for this כזית kezayis *kezayit*, and therefore, it is
still legitimate to do a היתר heter נדרים *heter nedarim* in this
case. So מיגו דמהני *migu d'mahani*, and once it's legitimate to do
it for the remaining כזית kezayis *kezayit*, then once we've done it,
we've completely, you know, we, you know, we have completely negated,
voided the שבועה shvua *shvua*. Okay, כי מיגו דמהני *ki migu d'mahani*.
מהני לה שאילה נמי אכזית קמא, it also works for all of
the earlier כזיתים and all of your earlier violations. We wouldn't do
it for that. That wouldn't be our focus. Our focus is for
the current כזית, kezayis but you need there to be a כזית.
kezayis You need there to be something that your שבועה shevuah is
still relevant toward. Okay, so that is a very elegant explanation. You
understand what the problem is and you understand what the חידוש chiddush
is, that it works as long as there's a כזית, kezayis it
doesn't work if it's all
past-oriented. ואיבעית אימא, ve'iba'is eima, the second answer is a little harder.
שלא אוכלנה, your שבועה shevuah. was I won't eat the whole loaf.
Okay?
השאיר כזית. hishir kezayis. Now why would therefore you need a כזית?
kezayis Right, as long as there's a little left, you haven't violated
yet. No, there's still a reason for כזית. kezayis השאיר כזית חשיב
ליה צלויי עליה ואי לא לא חשיב ליה צלויי עליה. hishir kezayis
chashiv lei tzaluyei alei ve'i lo lo chashiv lei tzaluyei alei. If
there's a כזית kezayis. left, it's important enough to go get a
שאילת חכם, sheilas chacham, and if not, it's not important enough. Now
that's a little bit funny, because because you would say, look, I
haven't violated yet. I want the חכם Chacham to get me out
of my נדר. neder. What difference does it make? So it seems
like, you know, I don't want to be constricted by it. But
it seems like that's exactly what the גמרא Gemara is saying here.
What's the big deal if you are constricted by it? So you
can't eat a half of a כזית. kezayis, You know what? Don't
waste my time. It's like coming to a בית דין Beis Din
for less than a פרוטה. perutah. I want my half penny back.
You know what? Don't waste my time. Like that's not a legitimate
enough thing to get us to deal with that case. You know
what? You're stuck with your נדר. neder? What's the relevance of being
stuck with your נדר? neder You won't be able to eat a
half a כזית. kezayit Big deal. Okay. So what? De minimis? De
minimis. Okay.
So too small to be...
Right. So therefore, yes, is your שבועה shevuah still relevant? Would our
התרת נדרים Hataras Nedarim work to get you out of a שבועה
shevuah that you have not yet violated? Yes. But you... it's not
important enough to get in the door just to eat half of
a כזית. kezayis Okay. So that is... so that seems to be
the answer. It makes a lot of sense. I should tell you
that תוספות Tosafos claims, and I don't really understand this, I mean
I understand what... תוספות Tosafos. says, I don't get it, says תוספות.
Tosafos If I take a שבועה shevuah. not to eat a loaf
of bread, now the גמרא Gemara makes it sound like I still
haven't violated until I ate that even if there's a half כזית
kezayis. left, I still haven't violated. So תוספות Tosafos says, let's say
there's a crumb left. תוספות Tosafos says, do you think that I'm
able to eat a whole loaf of bread and not leave over
any crumbs? So תוספות Tosafos thinks that I violate as soon as
there's less than a כזית kezayit left. Anything less than a כזית
kezayit doesn't matter and I've already violated. Okay, because he asks, or
else how do you like... what do you do like... do I
have to eat every single crumb? So therefore, but then תוספות Tosafos.
got a problem with this גמרא's Gemara answer. Because then the point
is like, okay, fine, you've already violated and there's nothing left moving
forward. So then why should... like you know, why is the גמרא
Gemara bothered with why it matters a כזית kezayit or less than
a כזית? The answer is obvious. If there's a כזית left, you
haven't violated yet. If there's less than a כזית left, you've already
violated and it's all in the past and it's too late. Right?
So the fact that the גמרא Gemara doesn't see a big qualitative
difference between the two seems to point against תוספות. Tosafos, But I
did want to mention that to you. For תוספות, Tosfos. if you
have a כזית left you haven't violated, less than a כזית you
have. According to that, it's obvious why you do... you would go
to... you would have a התרת נדרים Hataras Nedarim when there's still
a כזית left and not when there's not a כזית left, because
then it's too late, you've already violated. But again, the גמרא Gemara
doesn't seem to feel there's such a bright line between those. The
simple reading of the גמרא Gemara is what רש״י Rashi says is:
even less than a כזית left, you still haven't violated if you
said the whole loaf. I don't know at what stage it would
be called crumbs. We would have to figure that out. Okay. But,
and therefore irrelevant. But less than a כזית left, you still haven't
violated. And even though you haven't violated, we're still not going to
do a התרת נדרים Hataras Nedarim if it's only about a tiny
amount, if it's only about less than a כזית.
Like flatbread anyway, it's probably like a pizza, it doesn't leave that
much crumbs. Oh, that could be, that's an interesting thought.
Okay, I mean it doesn't have like a hard shell that would
crumb up. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara maybe it goes by
the definition of crumbs for פסח, Pesach, like if it's only crumbs
you don't have to do בדיקה bedika on it. Okay. מיתיבי. maseivei.
Now anyway, this is רבא's Rava. basic point. רבא's Rava point is
that you cannot do a התרת נדרים Hataras Nedarim if it's all
in the past. You can only do a התרת נדרים, Hataras Nedarim,
or התרת שבועה hataras shavua I should say, if it has some
future relevance. Once you're allowed to, then it also works for the
past, but that's his basic principle. Okay, מיתיבי, maseivei, I'll ask you
on this position of רבא. Rava מי שנדר שתי נזירות, mi shenadar
shtei neziros, we're going to go back to a נזיר nazir again.
Somebody took an oath to do two נזירות. neziros. ומנה ראשונה והפריש
לה קרבן. umana rishona vehifrish lah korban.
He counted the first one and separated out a קרבן. korban. ואחר
כך נשאל על הראשונה, ve'achar kach nishal al harishona, right, we had
this yesterday. And then before bringing the קרבן korban apparently, he went
ahead and he did a התר heter for the first, you know,
he got a שאילה, he did a התר heter for the first
one. עלתה לו שניה בראשונה, alsa lo shniya berishona, the second one
now takes the place of the first and your thirty days of
נזירות neziros was all now retroactively we see doing the second. Okay,
anyway, so why is that a challenge? Okay, because we assume, I
don't know why we assume this, to me it would be a
straight evidence for רבא. Rava It says you separated your קרבן. korban.
It didn't say you brought your קרבן. korban. It sounds like that
it still works because it's still relevant. The future relevance of it
is do I have to bring the קרבן korban or not? But
the גמרא Gemara somehow thinks that the case is you already brought
your קרבן korban and therefore it says ah, look, you can do
a שאלה she'ilah. even after even if it's all in the past.
So the גמרא Gemara says הכא במאי עסקינן בשלא כיפר. hacha mai
askinan bishelo kipper. Oh no, we're talking that you haven't brought the
קרבן korban yet, which I thought was פשט. Anyway, and therefore it
is still future-oriented and that's why you can do a שאלה. So
the גמרא Gemara. says הא תניא כיפר. ha tanya kipper. Wait, but
we have a ברייתא Baraita that says that even after you brought
your קרבן korban you can do a שאלה. So that sounds, that's
a more explicit contradiction to רבא. Rava That sounds like even though
it's all in the past you can still do a היתר. heter.
So the גמרא Gemara says בשלא גילח. bishelo gilach. You didn't shave
your head, which is what a נזיר nazir does. So there is
still something left for which the נדר neder is still relevant and
that's why you can do your היתר נדרים. ורבי אליעזר היא veRabbi
Eliezer hi and it's רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer דאמר תגלחת מעכבא. d'amar
tiglachas me'akeva.
Now it's not anything is left of it, right? It has to
be something of substance before we, right? So remember that whole discussion
of less than a כזית, whatever. Anyway, so therefore it's only if
something that is still preventing your obligation from having been satisfied. If
תגלחת tiglachas is a מצוה mitzvah but it doesn't really prevent your
נזירות nezirus from ending and you from being יוצא, yotzei, your whole
קרבנות, korbanos, then we wouldn't say that your נדר neder is still
future relevant. But if the shaving prevents you from fulfilling your obligations,
okay, then your נדר neder is still relevant and that's why you
can still go ahead and do it. So that's how it would
work into רבא's Rava framework. So the גמרא Gemara says הא תניא
גילח. ha tanya gilach.
One minute, but we have a ברייתא Baraita that says it works
even after you shaved. Even after you brought your קרבן, korban, even
after you shaved. So at least according to the ברייתא Baraita it
sounds like the whole point it's making is that you can do
a היתר for your נזירות nezirus even if it's all in the
past. So אמר רב אשי, amar Rav Ashi, and so רב אשי
says תגלחת tiglachas אמר רב אשי amar Rav Ashi נזירות קא רמית?
nezirus ka ramis? Wait, you're asking him from a נזירות nezirus case?
No, that's not a question. מי גרם לשנייה שלא
תחול ראשונה ואינה? mi garam lishniyah shelo tachol rishonah ve'einah? What prevented
the second one from taking effect, the second נזירות? nezirus? Your first
one and now the first one doesn't exist. What does that mean?
It's a nice little answer. I like רב אשי. So the answer
is very simple. רב אשי says look guys, if this guy only
had one נזירות, nezirus, not two נזירות, nezirus, okay, we wouldn't do
a היתר after he had brought his קרבנות. korbanos. Why are we
doing a היתר after he's brought his קרבנות? korbanos? Because what is
the effect, what does the fact that he has two נזירות nezirus
mean? That after he's done with his second one, what did we
learn yesterday? After he's done with his first one, if he did,
the second one takes effect, he's got to now do his second
one, right? So therefore in this case, as long as the second
one is still hovering, right, the first one remains relevant. It's not
all in the past. Why is the first one not all in
the past? Because it's because of the first one that I right
now have to keep a second נזירות. nezirus. If it hadn't been
for the first one, then I would have kept my second נזירות
nezirus earlier, right? You get that? So therefore he says it's not
like if I now want to go to a חכם Chacham after
I've brought my קרבן korban and done the whole thing, the גמרא
Gemara. says well, your first נזירות nezirus is no longer relevant, I
can't do a היתר. What are you talking about? Of course it's
relevant. It's because of it that I do the second one. If
you would get me out of it, then I wouldn't have to
do the second one, this second one would have been יוצא yotzei
for the first. So it's because even after you've completed it its
impact is still set, the fact that it took effect earlier is
still relevant to what I am doing right now, allows me to
go to a חכם Chacham right now and say I'm still dealing
with the burden as it were of my first נזירות. nezirus. The
burden of my first נזירות nezirus is what's forcing me now to
keep this second one. If you can just get me out of
my first נזירות, nezirus, I'll be able to put this second one
in the past and be done with it. Okay, so the fact
that right now the first one is making you live with a
challenge, that allows me to go to a חכם. Chacham. Okay, if
I only had one נזירות nezirus and I was done with it,
I can't go to a חכם Chacham and say please get me
out of the נזירות nezirus I just completed. Okay, so our case
of a שבועה shevuah, is like the case of one נזירות. nezirus.
Okay, I took a שבועה, shevuah, if it's all in the past,
I violated it, I didn't violate it, whatever, why am I going
to a חכם Chacham now? I can't go to a חכם Chacham.
for something in the past. Okay, based on this parallel by the
way, let's say I took a double שבועה. shevuah. Let's say I
said, oh no, that wouldn't work
because it wouldn't work, because if I violated it there's nowhere left
for the second שבועה shevuah? to take effect. Okay, I'd have to
think about a case where it would be relevant. But anyway,
oh here's a case, here's a case, no, alright I can't think
of a case offhand that would be relevant.
Well the case, the case of the loaf of bread, I took,
I'm not going to eat this loaf today, I'm not going to
eat... this other loaf tomorrow, and I was one כזית short of
finishing?
Yeah, but then, but the first one wouldn't impact whether I do
the second one. I'd have to think of it, maybe if you
stipulated a condition or something like that. Anyway, doesn't matter. Okay, but
that's the basic answer. The Gemara's answer is: Yes, Rava can hold
his position. If it's all in the past, you can't go to
a חכם. Chacham. If it's currently relevant you can, and the case
of the נזיר Nazir is even if you're feeling done with your
first נזירות, nezirut, it's not all in the past. Its impact is
being... you're dealing with its implications right now. Right now it's forcing
you to keep a second נזירות. nezirut. One minute, that's Rava. Rav
Ashi, now Rav Ashi disagrees. I'm sorry, did I skip a line?
No, Rav Ashi was the answer. Amemar amar, Amemar disagrees with Rava.
אפילו אכלו כולו נשאל עליו. afilu achlo kula nishal alav. I don't
agree with Rava. Even if something is all in the past and
you completely violated your נדר neder. or violated your שבועה shevuah and
there's no current relevance, you can go to a חכם Chacham and
he will retroactively void it and you will be free from that
violation.
Now, why? I maybe said it a little too facilely. Because he
says, you know what, it's never all in the past. Why is
it never all in the past? Because אי בשוגג מחוסר קרבן. ei
beshogeig mechusar korban. If you violated בשוגג, beshogeig, okay, and you want
to get out of your בשוגג beshogeig sin, well, going to a
חכם Chacham, still has current relevance. What's the current relevance? That he
would exempt you from bringing a קרבן. korban. Okay, so even though
the שבועה shevuah. isn't binding me to act in a certain way,
the fact of the שבועה shevuah. in the past still has relevance
to me right now; it obligates me in a קרבן korban because
I violated it. So that fact that I'm obligated a קרבן korban
and I want to get out of that קרבן korban allows me
to go to the חכם. Chacham אי במזיד, ei bemeizid, if I
violated it willfully, so מחוסר מלקות. mechusar malkot. Ha! Imagine בית דין
Beis Din ever trying to give somebody lashes for violating this. Wait,
I want to go to a חכם. Chacham. Okay, if I violated
it willfully then the current relevance is that the בית דין Beis
Din is going to catch up with me and give me מלקות.
malkot. Okay, and therefore it'd be a valid reason.
And if the חכם Chacham says: How do you know you'd get
מלקות? malkot?
Exactly, exactly. So anyway, so he says all of it does have
current relevance. Now of course there are cases where that wouldn't be
true. Let's say I did it willfully without warning, right? So then
there's no מלקות malkot relevance anymore. Let's say I did it willfully
without witnesses. Let's say I did it בשוגג beshogeig but it was
one of those בשוגג beshogeig we mentioned earlier that technically I'm not
obligated in a קרבן, korban, right? There's some debates about what those
בשוגג beshogeig are, I remember about שוגג של שבועה, shogeig shel shvua,
שוגג של חפץ. shogeig shel chefetz. So Rav Ashi seems to, I
overstated Amemar. Amemar doesn't seem to, or not doesn't seem, he's not
saying you don't need current relevance to do a התרה, hatara, he's
just willing to expand that scope of current relevance. Maybe there are
some cases you can't go to a חכם, Chacham but in a
case where you're חייב chayav a קרבן korban or you would be
חייב מלקות, chayav malkus. you can go to get because that is
its current impact. Now, let's say you're חייב chayav מלקות malkot, אבל
כפתוהו על העמוד. aval kaftuhu al ha'amud. There they were, they took
you to בית דין, Beis Din, they got the witnesses, you had
the warning, they put you on the beating post, and the guy
was getting out his whip, and then you said, Wait, is there
a חכם Chacham? here?
So in that case לא, lo, you can't go to a חכם.
chacham Why? Isn't it still relevant whether the guy's going to lash
you or not? כי שמואל, ki Shmuel, like שמואל, Shmuel, דאמר שמואל,
d'amar Shmuel, כפתוהו על העמוד ורץ מבית דין פטור. kaftuhu al ha'amud
veratz mibeis din patur. Once they bound you up to a post
and you ran away from the בית דין, Beis Din, you would
be somehow you'd be exempt. Once it got to that stage, if
you managed to escape, you wouldn't have to they wouldn't give you
מלקות.
malkot ונקלה אחיך לעיניך. venikla achicha l'einecha.
Right, well that's what we're going to say. But presumably what Amemar
is saying is that maybe at this stage it's like you already
got your מלקות, malkot. so it's even though you haven't, I mean
for you it matters, but conceptually and halachically, right, or halachically you've
already got your מלקות. malkot, So therefore it's too late for you
to ask on it, it's like you already got it, something along
those
lines. Okay. So, ולא היא, v'lo hi, but you know what, that's
not true, it's not like you already got it. התם רץ, hatam
ratz, there you ran away, and the running away as Michael remembered
Rashi says ונקלה אחיך לעיניך, venikla achicha l'einecha, that's like shameful, that
is what substitutes for the מלקות. malkot. הכא לא רץ, hacha lo
ratz, here you didn't run away. So it's not being bound to
the post makes it as if you've already gotten your מלקות. malkot.
No you haven't, it's still relevant. So up to that very last
minute, it's almost like a nice metaphor for תשובה, teshuva, you know,
עד יום מותו תחכה לו. ad yom moto techakeh lo. There you
are, you know, the guillotine over the head, or I mean whatever,
up to the last minute you can go to the חכם chakham,
and, you know, the same way you go to God and do
תשובה, teshuva, you can go to the חכם even at that last
second, even when it's just to get out of the punishment and
retroactively undo it and whatever and be exempt from that מלקות. malkot.
You can still because it's not like you've already got your מלקות.
malkot.
But wouldn't בית דין Beis Din meaning would they facilitate you going
to the חכם?
That's a different question. That's the business of how
to get there.
That's a different question. Exactly, Charlie, yes.
Yeah, so I was going to ask about the נזיר Nazir thing
whether... Or anything and that you can get it the
נזירות neziros nullified even after you brought the קרבנות. korbanos.
But the קרבנות korbanos were for the first נזירות neziros that didn't
even... didn't exist.
Right, but now retroactively they were for the... right, that's okay, it
all works retroactively. The קרבנות korbanos would work retroactively for the second
one if you undo the first one. Yeah.
Why would you want to undo the first one if you already
brought the קרבנות? korbanos? I mean what to...
to get out of having to do the second one. Oh. Right?
Because now the second one became the first.
Now
the second one was the first. Now retroactively...
yeah... yeah.
You did the second.
Right. Okay, exactly. אמר רבא. Now רבא has another statement here and
this used a huge תוספות. Tosfos, And this huge תוספות, Tosfos sometimes
תוספות Tosfos is dealing with other גמרות Gemaras or whatever. This huge
תוספות Tosfos is just trying to get פשט in the גמרא. Gemara
Okay. There's also like a huge רש"י. Rashi. What did they think
about רש"י?
Rashi? Yeah, exactly.
I will try... well the first half of תוספות Tosfos. basically asks
ten questions on רש"י Rashi and says wait, this part of רש"י
Rashi doesn't make sense, that part of רש"י Rashi doesn't make sense.
It's funny anyway. Very expository type of תוספות. Tosfos Anyway, so let's
take a look. I will try to simplify this גמרא Gemara and
we'll see if I succeed. אמר רבא שבועה שלא אוכל כיכר זו
אם אוכל זו. Amar Rava, Shevuah she'lo ochal kikar zo im ochal
zo. I won't eat bread A if I eat B. Okay?
So A is the שבועה shevuah. bread, we'll call it, and B
is the תנאי t'nai bread. How about I won't eat
B if I eat A? What? How about I won't eat B
if I eat
it? Let's... well, okay.
All right, I mean fine. We'll do it that way anyway because
that fits with the way תוספות Tosfos falls. תוספות Tosfos. refers to
it... if that makes you happier,
okay.
Okay. Here's
your two loaves of bread. You've got A and B. We'll call
A the תנאי t'nai and B the שבועה. shevuah Okay? This is
my person.
I won't eat B
if I eat A. Okay? So now, that's the case. All right?
Let's take a look. ואכל את הראשונה בשוגג והשנייה במזיד. Ve'achal es
harishonah beshogeg vehasheniyah bemeizid. Now I am going to explain this like
תוספות. Tosfos I'll bore you later about what רש"י Rashi and רבינו
תם Rabbeinu Tam say. But תוספות' Tosfos. explanation while it's a little
bit... requires you buy into it to a read of the text,
it conceptually is by far the simplest. Okay. He says the ראשונה
rishonah here like Michael said means what we're calling the one of
the condition, the ראשונה. rishonah. Even if the way the גמרא Gemara
framed it was first he said I won't eat this if I
eat this, he might have said the conditional loaf second, but conceptually
it's the first. This one triggers the fact that the שבועה shevuah
takes effect on B. If you never eat A, right? You will
never... you're never restricted from B. I'm going to call this the
trigger.
Okay. So that's why it's called the first because it's the trigger.
It makes B take effect. So whichever order you eat this in,
we're calling this the first. You could eat this second but we're
calling it the first because it's the one that triggers the שבועה
shevuah to take effect. Okay. And here is the one thing you
have to know for תוספות. Tosfos, When... remember there's a הלכה... halachah...
on the one hand, to be חייב chayav a קרבן korban you
have to eat the thing בשוגג. beshogeg. You have to have forgotten
your שבועה. shevuah? Okay. On the other hand, when you take a
שבועה, shavuah. you have to know what you're doing, right? It's אדם
בשבועה. adam beshevuah. If you're אונס, ones, if you think somehow that
you're... if you have a misunderstanding, if you're swearing about the past
and you think you're telling the truth, it's not a binding שבועה,
shavuah, right? We learned that before. That idea that you have to
be like conscious of and of your right mind when you're taking
a שבועה. shavuah So that leads to the following point.
The requirements to bring a קרבן korban are going to be... this
is from תוספות, Tosafot, it's very easy because...
okay. What is the requirement to bring a קרבן korban when you
eat this? What state do you have to be in? בשוגג beshogeg
or במזיד? bemeizid? בשוגג. beshogeg.
בשוגג. beshogeg. If you're במזיד bemeizid you don't bring a קרבן. korban.
What state do you have to be in when you're triggering the
שבועה? shavuah The חידוש chiddush is no, it does because the חידוש
chiddush is that since the שבועה shavuah, doesn't take effect without the
trigger, the trigger is considered part of the act of taking the
שבועה. shavuah And therefore the... this is the assumption... you know, everybody
sort of says that in their read of the גמרא. Okay, but
question is where do you say it. But anyway, here you have
to be במזיד. bemeizid. במזיד bemeizid in the sense of being aware
that by eating this I am triggering the שבועה. shavuah. Otherwise it's
not like you consciously took the שבועה. sh'vuah Why?
I just remembered not to eat B.
I understand, but this makes the שבועה sh'vuah, take effect. So the
חידוש chiddush is that the trigger is considered part of the act
of taking the שבועה sh'vuah, since it's required for the שבועה sh'vuah.
to take effect. So you have to be conscious here. Okay. That...
now... now that we understand that we'll totally be able to read...
you have to be conscious while you're eating A? Even though you're
conscious when you made the שבועה?
shvuah, I understand that's the חידוש. chiddush. That is the חידוש. chiddush.
Okay. Good thing you don't have to worry about רש"י. Rashi. רש"י
Rashi would get even more upset. Okay, so anyway this makes a
lot of sense. I understand you wouldn't necessarily have assumed it, but
that's the position of רבא that you have to be conscious when
you're eating the trigger. Okay, so... So and now כי גוונא דאמרן
ki gavna d'amran ואכלה הראשונה בשוגג והשנייה במזיד. v'achla harishona b'shogeg v'hashniya
b'meizid. So if this was שוגג shogeg and this was מזיד, meizid,
you're certain—by the reverse—you're certainly not going to bring a קרבן, korban,
okay? Because this didn't—this didn't trigger the שבועה. shvuah So once this
didn't trigger the שבועה, shvuah, it doesn't really matter what state you
ate this in; the שבועה shvuah. wasn't triggered, okay? You're פטור. patur.
ראשונה במזיד—again, Rishona b'meizid by the way, it doesn't matter what order
you ate them in, okay? That's a—they're just calling it ראשונה rishona
and שנייה, shniya, but according to תוספות, Tosafot it does not matter
what order.
No, no, doesn't matter
what order because let me explain, then you'll ask your question. ראשונה
במזיד ושנייה בשוגג חייב. Rishona b'meizid v'shniya b'shogeg chayav. That's the case
we have here. The only way you're חייב chayav is if the
trigger—if you were conscious when you were—when you were pulling the trigger,
or whatever, and then the act itself was done בשוגג, b'shogeg, because
then it—because then you're not consciously violating. Okay? שתיהן בשוגג פטור. Shteihen
b'shogeg patur. If they're both בשוגג, b'shogeg, you're פטור, patur, because then
you didn't trigger it. Now, שתיהן במזיד. Shteihen b'meizid. Let's say they're
both במזיד, b'meizid, okay? So you triggered it, that's מזיד. meizid. You
ate this במזיד. b'meizid. So you're willfully violating. But now the order
matters, because now if you ate this one first במזיד, b'meizid, when
you ate it, you didn't do anything wrong; you hadn't triggered the
שבועה shvuah. yet. So here is the first case where order matters,
okay? So
שתיהן במזיד, Shteihen b'meizid, so אכלה לתנאי והדר אכלה לאיסורי. achala l'tnai
v'hadar achala l'issurei. So if you ate this first במזיד, b'meizid, you
triggered it, and then you ate this במזיד—it b'meizid was already totally
in effect, and you were willingly violating, and you're חייב chayav מלקות.
malkot. מחייב—you Mechayev get מלקות. malkus. Now we're talking about
מלקות. malkus. אכלה לאיסורי והדר אכלה לתנאי. Achala l'issurei v'hadar achala l'tnai.
But let's say you ate this first, and when you were eating
this, you weren't even doing anything wrong yet, okay? And only when
you ate that, you did something wrong. Now, you would say—so you
could say, so give the guy התראה hasrah before he eats this
one, and say, Buddy, if you eat that תנאי, tnai, then you're
going to have retroactively triggered your שבועה, shvuah. you're going to have
caused your שבועה shvuah. to have been a violation; don't eat that
תנאי, tnai, you'll violate the איסור. issur. And he says, I don't
care, and he eats it anyway. So the—you might think that that
would get him מלקות, malkus, but it doesn't. Because this isn't the
act of איסור. issur. The warning can only come associated with the
violation, not the thing that retroactively makes an act I did yesterday
into a violation. You have to warn me about my act that
is the transgression itself. Okay? So אכלה לתנאי והדר—I achala l'tnai v'hadar
already said that. So אכלה לאיסורי והדר אכלה לתנאי, achala l'issurei v'hadar
achala l'tnai, פלוגתא דרבי יוחנן וריש לקיש. plugta d'Rabbi Yochanan v'Reish Lakish.
That would be a debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and ריש
לקיש. Reish Lakish. למאן דאמר התראת ספק שמה התראה חייב. l'man d'amar
hasra'as safek shmah hasra'ah chayav. למאן דאמר לא שמה התראה פטור. l'man
d'amar lav shmah hasra'ah patur. You might remember they debate whether you
give a guy warning and you don't know at the time you're
giving him warning whether he's going to violate or not. Okay? So
here, when he eats this במזיד, b'meizid, the only place you can
give warning is at the act of violation. But when he's doing
that act of violation, when he did that yesterday and he ate
that loaf, that act of transgression—it wasn't an act of transgression then;
actually, ironically, it was completely permissible for him to eat that loaf
at that time. Yes, I know that if I wind up eating
the other loaf, this will be forbidden, but I haven't eaten the
other loaf and I don't plan on eating the other loaf and
I'm going to eat it. Okay, so—so that's when you needed to
give him warning when he was doing it; it was totally permissible.
But ריש לקיש Reish Lakish would say it's still possible to give
him warning. You could say, Buddy, if you eat that and then
you go ahead and eat the second one, this will be a
transgression of your שבועה. shvuah, And he says, אף על פי כן,
af al pi kein, and he goes ahead and eats it. So
according to ריש לקיש, Reish Lakish, that counted as sufficient warning and—and
therefore you had the warning, you had the willful—he ate it—retroactively he
would have violated. I have to tell you that I—I struggle with
that because the normal case of התראת ספק hasra'as safek for ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish is more
like—is more like a case where the person is like in the
process of violating, but it hasn't yet clarified whether he will transgress.
Like a good example would be he's leaving over his meat for
his קרבן, korban, okay? And it's got it in my
fridge, and you're telling me, Dov, you gotta eat that meat; in
one hour, it's going to be the end of the day and
you'll have transgressed, no? And you say, Yeah, I know, but I'm
in the middle of my TV show, stop bothering me. You know?
So therefore you're like warning is like prodding me to do something
where my inaction—and I'm, you know—my inaction is showing a disregard, right?
So like, but let's say, I'll give you another scenario. Let's say
I was eating the meat. You know, there was 20 pounds to
eat. I was eating the meat. And you said, Dov, you gotta
hurry up and eat it because if you don't hurry up and
eat it—and I says, I know, I am working on it, I'm
hurrying up, okay? But—but don't forget, if you don't eat it, fine,
stop bothering me, I'm eating it. And then I don't. wind up
eating it all. Would you say oh that was good התראה hasra
because he told me? Right? Like it wasn't like you normally think
one of the goals of התראה hasra is not just to make
me aware of the fact, but to make me actually seen in
my act to like to be disregarding, right? To sort of be
like saying אף על פי כן, af al pi chen, I don't
care, this doesn't mean anything to me, I you know, to heck
with it, right? That we normally feel is part of what the
act of of ignoring the התראה hasra is, right? So like when
if I'm eating this loaf, and it's totally permissible, and I have
no plans to eat this other loaf, why am I showing you
a disregard for the prohibition? Like if I asked a rabbi is
it allowed for me to eat this loaf? Yes. Even לכתחילה? Yes,
just be careful not to eat the other loaf. So like it's
hard to see that as an act- did the person who gave
me warning inform me of the possible consequences? Yes. Did I do
an act of disregarding the התראה? hasra? Like no, you know, I
don't think so. So it's interesting to apply ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
to this type of a case. Anyway that's what the גמרא says,
according to תוספות Tosafot that's the basic idea. You need this to
be במזיד b'meizid as the trigger. Then if this is במזיד b'meizid
as the trigger, if this is שוגג shogeig you bring a קרבן,
korban, and if this is מזיד meizid you go ahead and you
and you what do you call it? And you then retroactive then
it depends which order it turned in, whether that was a clear
violation במזיד b'meizid or only a retroactive you know whether that was
a clear violation at the time you were doing it or if
the order was different, only retroactively a violation and then it gets
into התראת ספק. hasras safeik.
Now what I'm understanding why are we bifurcating cases in which order
matters and it doesn't? I mean is it because- Show
me a case where you think order wouldn't matter?
I think it matters in every case. I mean is it because-
Any case you did- any case you did- Is it because he
said I won't eat B if- if he would have said I
won't eat B if I eat A first, then would that have
changed?
Yes, but you didn't say that.
Why don't we say that's what he meant?
Okay, that's a different point because he- first of all we're not
going to read that. You just said- you just said it like
that. Why should we read in- alright fine, but we're not going
to read that order into it. Okay, so think about it: order's
going to matter. Any case this is a שוגג, shogeig, the conversation
stops there, right? Because it didn't trigger it. And if this is
a מזיד, meizid, so if this is a מזיד meizid and this
is a שוגג, shogeig, so then why should order matter? Whether this
was a שוגג shogeig earlier or later? If this was מזיד meizid
and this was מזיד, meizid, that's the case that order matters and
that's the case we were discussing. Now that's how תוספות Tosafot reads
it. רש"י, Rashi, just for a- you to be aware, רש"י Rashi
says that actually
it's not that the- it's not that this- that you need to
be- when the- when we say you need to be conscious מזיד
meizid as it were for the שבועה shvuah to be triggered, רש"י
Rashi says it's not when you eat the תנאי. t'nai. It's whichever
one is the first one you need to be conscious of what
you're doing, which is a bizarre idea. Like that because you know
you totally understand תוספות Tosafot that's the first- that if we're going
to say that you need to be like מזיד meizid like conscious
and willful, that it's not only the שבועה, shvuah. that it's also
the תנאי t'nai which triggers it, you understand it. Why we should
say it also have to be the first one you eat regardless
of the first order is a strange idea that's what רש"י Rashi
says. I don't want to go into it. That's why תוספות's Tosafot.
read although it requires saying ראשונה rishona means תנאי t'nai and שניה
sh'niya means שבועה, shvuah, okay so it's a little bit of a
textual you know force, but it's a very conceptually a very clean,
a very simple thing to be saying. Okay. One other interesting-
yeah I was trying to remember what רבנו תם- Rabbeinu Tam רבנו
תם Rabbeinu Tam had an interesting חידוש. chiddush.
Yes,
I think I'll double
check. Without giving you the whole read of רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam
I'll just tell you his basic
חידוש. chiddush.
רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam said that you don't have to eat the
תנאי t'nai במזיד b'meizid in order to trigger the שבועה. shvuah And
רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam actually has the following scenario: you ate this
one
במזיד b'meizid first, this one you ate במזיד b'meizid first and then
okay and at the time remember you weren't doing anything wrong. And
then you ate the- this one, forgetting you had made the whole
stipulation. So רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam says in that case even though
you ate this one willfully, you're considered a שוגג shogeig and you
bring a קרבן korban because the thing that made you transgress when
you ate this you were allowed to eat this consciously and the
thing that made you transgress was you ate this, that is what
created the transgression and when so therefore he says if you were
שוגג shogeig if you'd forgotten about it when you ate this, then
you're going to bring a קרבן korban because we consider the whole
thing to be בשוגג b'shogeig even though this eating was done intentionally.
Okay, so that's some of like what רש"י Rashi and רבנו תם
Rabbeinu Tam say about this but again not to confuse you if
you just go like תוספות. Tosafos, it's a very clean read. Okay?
If this is בשוגג, beshogeg, the conversation stops, it doesn't matter what
order it is, order doesn't matter. If this is במזיד, bemeizid, then
your תנאי tnai took effect and then we could talk about whether
this was בשוגג beshogeg or this was במזיד. bemeizid. Yes? I just
wanted to go back to my question.
You said רש לקיש Reish Lakish said you could give a warning
on the trigger?
No, you give a warning on this. Yes.
There was something that...
No, you can't give a warning on the trigger. The warning has
to take place when you're doing the act that's going to be
the violation, but for רש לקיש Reish Lakish it could be a
warning to say, hey, what I'm doing is totally permissible. I know,
but if you wind up eating the other one, you're going to
have made an עבירה. aveirah. Fine, thank you very much, that's not
my plan. And somehow that would still count as an התראה hatraah
for רש לקיש. Reish Lakish. Okay, even though what the guy was
doing at the time was completely permissible. Okay, now the גמרא says
like this.
תלן זו בזו. talan zo be-zo. Let's say, too bad Michael isn't
here, let's say here's how you frame it. Okay,
תלן זו בזו. talan zo be-zo. You made them interdependent. לא אוכל
זו אם אוכל זו, זו אוכל זו אם אוכל זו. lo ochel
zo im ochel zo, zo ochel zo im ochel zo. Okay, I
won't eat A if I eat B, and I won't eat B
if I eat A. Okay, so basically what you have going on
here is two layers. Okay,
you have two תנאים. tnaim. I mean two, right, statements. Okay, you
have statement number one where this is the trigger and this is
a שבועה, shvuah, and your statement number two where this is the
שבועה shvuah and this is the trigger.
Okay?
And
they're basically just sitting one on top of the other. So it's
going to be like the same type of thing except we're just
having a little fun here. Okay? We like it like, you know,
like again as I told you, I had a רבי Rebbi once
who said, this is what they did when they didn't have TV.
Okay, so,
okay, you can just imagine. Oh wait, wait, I got a brain
teaser! Let's
say... Okay, so לא אוכל זו אם אוכל זו, לא אוכל זו
אם אוכל זו. lo ochel zo im ochel zo, lo ochel zo
im ochel zo. ואכל זו במזיד עצמה ובשגגת חבירה וזו במזיד עצמה
ובשגגת חבירתה. ve-achal zo be-meizid atzmah u-ve-shigegat chavera ve-zo be-meizid atzmah u-ve-shigegat
chavertah. Okay, so when I ate A, okay, what was my state
of mind?
I remembered the first שבועה, shvuah okay, and I had forgotten
the second שבועה. shvuah. Okay, so when I ate this, I knew
I was triggering the first one and I had forgotten that I
had actually made the whole second thing at all. Then when I
came to eat B, okay, the same thing. Okay, I remembered
that I made the first one and I forgot that I made...
wait, is that right? No, no, the other way around. Okay, when
I came to eat
B, I remembered the second one and I forgot that I had
made the first one.
Okay, so now we know what the answer is, right?
Because the trigger in both cases was intentional and the eating was
unintentional. Boom, two קרבנות. korbanot.
Okay, זו במזיד עצמה ובשגגת חבירתה, zo be-meizid atzmah u-ve-shigegat chavertah, חייב,
chayav, you're חייב. chayav. Okay, שתיהן, shteihen, right...
did I skip a line?
ואכל זו במזיד עצמה.
ve-achal zo be-meizid
atzmah. Oh, במזיד עצמה, be-meizid atzmah, the עצמה atzmah means the שבועה.
shvuah. I just jumped to the second case. I'm sorry. עצמה atzmah
means the one that is the שבועה. shvuah. חבירתה chavertah means the
one... meaning the other one is the שבועה. shvuah So this was
במזיד be-meizid and this was שוגג. shogeg. And then the other one
was במזיד עצמה, be-meizid atzmah, עצמה atzmah is the שבועה, shvuah and
this was שוגג. shogeg. So in this case, the triggers were שוגג,
shogeg, you're obviously פטור. patur. Okay, so in that case,
פטור. patur. זו בשגגת עצמה ובמזיד חבירתה וזו בשגגת עצמה ובמזיד חבירתה,
zo be-shigegat atzmah u-ve-meizid chavertah ve-zo be-shigegat atzmah u-ve-meizid chavertah, חייב. chayav.
If it's the reverse, which is what I did before, okay, this
is שגגת עצמה. shigegat atzmah. The שוגג shogeg one, when I was
eating B, the שוגג shogeg one I was שוגג shogeg on the
fact that it was intrinsically a שבועה shvua, and I was aware
that it was a trigger. And when I was eating A, I
was שוגג shogeg on the fact that it was itself אסור, assur,
but I remembered that it was a trigger. Okay? So in that
case, the trigger was intentional, and then you have the שוגג shogeg
eating, and in that
case, right, one proactively, one retroactively, whatever, if I ate it in
whatever order. Anyway, in that case, I bring two קרבנות. korbanot. Okay,
וזו בשגגת חבירה, ve-zo be-shigegat chavera, חייב, chayav, you're חייב. chayav. Man,
imagine teaching this without a whiteboard. Okay, שתיהן בשוגג פטור. shteihen be-shogeg
patur. If you were completely שוגג shogeg throughout, you'd be פטור patur
because the triggers were triggered בשוגג. be-shogeg. Okay,
שתיהן במזיד. shteihen be-meizid. Now, let's say everything was במזיד be-meizid when
I was eating... I knew exactly what I was doing. I knew
that it was a trigger and I knew that it was and
I knew that it was itself אסור assur had the other thing
been triggered. Okay, so now we're back to getting מלקות. malkus. Okay,
this one you if this was the order you ate it in,
then this one you definitely get מלקות, malkus, because when you were
eating this you were it'd already been triggered. And this one is
debatable because the trigger is only retroactively, right? Right.
So השנייה מחייב, hashniya mechayev, so the second
one when you ate the second one, because you did it in
this order, when you ate the second one then you clearly transgressed
after it had been triggered. You definitely get מלקות malkus on the
you know, when you ate the first one, right, A being the
first one, there you only transgressed retroactively. ראשונה פלוגתא דרבי יוחנן וריש
לקיש. rishona plugta de'Rabbi Yochanan ve'Reish Lakish. Okay, that was all very
nice. See how easy that was? If you just adopt Tosafot's reading
and you use a whiteboard it all works out very well. Now
you have to put in there what happens if you have a
כזית here and a כזית. Go to a חכם and he might
say... Right, exactly. אמר רב מרי, amar Rav Mari, אף אנן נמי
תנינא. af anan nami tenina. We taught similarly now again the way
this is being read is we taught similarly that you need to
be aware of what you're doing when you trigger the שבועה. shvua
Okay, you need to be מזיד mezid when you trigger the שבועה,
shvua even though you've already taken the שבועה shvua and you were
conscious of what you were doing, that this idea that you have
to be sort of conscious of the שבועה, shvua. you know, is
not only limited to the act of taking it but also to
the trigger. All right, so let's take a look. נדרי שגגות. nidrei
shegagos. We have a הלכה halacha that I mean, you know, it's
a משנה mishna. that follows the line of ארבעה נדרים. arba'ah nedarim.
I'll read the parentheses which is the beginning of the משנה. Okay,
ארבעה נדרים התירו חכמים, arba'ah nedarim hitiru chachamim, four types of נדר.
neder נדרי זירוזין נדרי הבאי נדרי שגגות נדרי אונסין. nidrei ziruzin nidrei
havai nidrei shegagos nidrei onasin. So נדרי שגגות כיצד? nidrei shegagos keitzad?
What's an example of שוגג? shogeg? Not so before we had you
took a שבועה shvua, in the past and you thought you were
telling the truth. Okay, but that basically is the principle that you
have to be sort of conscious of the fact that you are
making a שבועה shvua. and the implications of it. כיצד. keitzad. So
this is a נדר neder. though, not a שבועה. shvua. קונם אם
אכלתי ואם שתיתי. konam im achalti ve'im shasisi. A person says, you
know, this bread is אסור assur to me as a קרבן korban
if I had anything to eat today. And you thought that you
didn't have anything to eat. You'd have to do both or one
or the other? It doesn't matter. We're not worried. We'll worry about
when we get to נדר. neder Okay. If I had anything to
eat or drink today. And you thought you hadn't. You totally thought
that you were you know, that you hadn't had breakfast yet or
whatever it was, you know, you forgot that you took that tiny
sip of coffee when you woke up first thing in the morning.
So you thought that it was not going to take effect. Okay.
ונזכר שאכל ושתה, venizkar she'achal veshasah, and then you remember, oh my
God, that's right, I did have that sip of coffee. Okay, guess
what? The נדר neder didn't take effect because as far as your
mind was, that נדר neder, would not have been effective because you
had thought that you had not satisfied the תנאי. tnai. Now that's
past tense. והוא הדין בשבועה vehu hadin bishvuah also applies to נדר,
neder right? Yes, exactly. And you had thought that you had not
satisfied the תנאי. tnai. Now that's at the time you were taking
it, that's not as much of a חידוש chiddush as the next
point. שאני אוכל. she'ani ochel. Now Rashi reads it as שאני אוכל.
she'ani ochel. When you learn נדרים it's crazy because every time you
don't know whether they're saying שאני she'ani or שאיני, she'eini, that I
will or that I won't. שאני אוכל שאני שותה. she'ani ochel she'ani
shoteh. Okay, let's say you say, the way Rashi reads this is,
this is forbidden to me as a קרבן korban if I, that's
the way he's reading שאני, she'ani, which would be like if I
eat or if I drink later today.
Okay, so you're making it stipulating based on a תנאי tnai you're
going to do.
שכח ואכל ושתה, shachach ve'achal veshasah, and then you forgot about what
you had said and you ate and drank. מותר, muttar, then it's
permissible to eat that first that loaf of bread you took a
נדר on because you did not trigger it consciously. Okay? So this
is being read basically as a support that look, it's not that
you just have to be conscious of what you're doing when you're
taking the שבועה. shvua. If you make it based on a future
condition, then you have to be conscious that you're triggering it when
you're triggering it. Okay? ותני עלה, vesani alah, we have a ברייתא
braisa on that that teaches: כשם שנדרי שגגות מותרים כך שבועות שגגות
מותרות, keshem shenidrei shegagos muttarim kach shvuos shegagos muttaros, that the same
thing would apply by a by a שבועה. shvua, And if we'll
just read the parentheses: שבועת שגגות היכי דמי, shvuat shegagos heichi dami,
what's a שבועה בשוגג? shvuah bishogeg? לאו כי האי גוונא, lav ki
hai gavna, it must be like our case: this is אסור, assur,
I won't eat this loaf of bread if I do this. So
you make it stipulated on a future תנאי tnai and then when
you trigger the תנאי tnai you forgot about it. שמע מינה, shmah
mina, that is a good proof. Okay, so for Tosafot it's very
easy. For Tosafot it really just boils down to one simple point
which is the point at the end: that if you make something
based on a תנאי tnai and a trigger, you have to be
conscious when you are doing that תנאי, tnai, eating that trigger, whatever
it is, you have to be conscious at that time that it's
causing the שבועה shvua to take effect. And if you had forgotten
about your whole stipulation, then the שבועה shvua does not take effect.
That's really all it boils down to, right, according to Tosafot. What
about this whole מוצא שפתיך תשמור, motza sefasecha tishmor, you know, you
got to like, you know, this seems to be, I mean, the
flip side is... I know, but it has to be, I understand,
but it has to do with the fact that the whole point
about פי ולבו שוים pi velibo shavin and how central an idea
of שבועת נדר shvuat neder is to your sort of express desire.
So it's not just a speech act as if divorced from what
you wanted. But you're right. I mean, I agree with you. There's
a lot of loopholes. How about the whole התרת נדרים hataras nedarim
is, you know, כהררים התלויים בשערה. kehararim hateluyim besa'ara. Okay. So anyway,
בשערה. besa'ara. So anyway, so the גמרא says like this: איפא Eifa
now we're going to have a funny little anecdote to the story.
I mean, halachic, but also it's like anyway. איפא תני שבועות בי
רבה. Eifa tani Shvuos be-rabba. איפא, Eifa, name of a certain חכם,
learned שבועות Shvuos in רבה Rabba's ישיבה. yeshiva. פגע ביה אבימי אחוה.
Paga be-Avimi achua. אבימי Avimi is brother bumped into him. אמר ליה,
amar lei, so אבימי Avimi said, 'Oh, let me ask you what
you're learning in ישיבה.' yeshiva. So he said to him, 'שבועה שלא
אכלתי שבועה שלא אכלתי מהו?' shvua she-lo achalti shvua she-lo achalti mahu?
If a guy takes a double שבועה, shvua, 'a שבועה shvua I
didn't eat bread in the past,' and then again he takes 'a
שבועה shvua, I didn't eat bread in the past.' Is he חייב
chayav for the second one? So we would say, oh that's a
שבועה חלה על שבועה. shvua chal al shvua. So he says, אמר
ליה, amar lei, אינו חייב אלא אחת. eino chayav ella achas. You
know, that only the first one, the second one is אין שבועה
חלה על שבועה. ein shvua chal al shvua? So אמר ליה, amar
lei, אשתבישתא. ishtabishata. You're being sloppy, you made a mistake. הרי יש
פה שבועה לשקר. harei yesh po shvua lishaker. The second שבועה shvua.
was a שבועה לשקר. shvua lishaker. When do we say אין שבועה
חלה על שבועה? ein shvua chal al shvua When it's future oriented.
This loaf is already forbidden. I'm already not allowed to do this.
I can't make myself doubly not allowed to do something. Right? That's
about a future oriented שבועה. shvua, A past שבועה, shvua as soon
as you said the first one, you're חייב chayav a שבועה לשקר.
shvua lishaker. It then goes away. There's no lasting sort of, you
know, effect of a past oriented שבועה. shvua. So now you take
a second false שבועה. shevuah That's also a false שבועה. shevuah. אין
שבועה shevuah חלה על שבועה shevuah is only a future oriented שבועה,
shevuah? not a past one. We had said that a couple of
weeks ago, it came up in passing, and once you say it,
it's obvious, but it might not have been the first thing you
were saying if you weren't thinking, you know, if you didn't think
it through. And that's going to be the running theme here, that
he basically just is showing his brother that his brother's not thinking
things through clearly. Okay. And he also tricks his brother a little
bit along the way, cause you know, he always gets his brother
to overcorrect in the opposite direction. So here his brother said אינו
חייב אלא אחת eino chayav ella achas and he says, 'No, you're
wrong, you're חייב שתים.' chayav shtayim. So now the brother is primed
to say חייב שתים, chayav shtayim, okay? And here's going to be
the next question. שבועה שלא אוכל תשע ועשר מהו? shvua she-lo ochal
tesha ve-eser mahu? Guy first says, 'A שבועה shevuah. I won't eat
nine olives,' and then he says, 'A שבועה shevuah, I won't eat
ten.' So what is it? So initially you think, oh that's a
bigger שבועה, shevuah it should take effect, because it's ten. And he
remember he had already primed his brother to say חייב, chayav, right?
So the brother says, חייב! chayav! Okay, you're חייב! chayav! Good! Last
time I made a mistake by saying it was only one, so
now I'll say fine, you're חייב chayav
for two, and anyway, ten is bigger than nine.
חייב על כל אחת ואחת. chayav al kol achas ve-achas. אמר ליה,
amar lei, אשתבישתא. ishtabishata. No, you're making a mistake again, you're being
sloppy. Why? Ten is actually not bigger than nine. The second שבועה
shevuah has to forbid more than the first. So if the first
one already forbade you to eat nine, if I'm forbidding to eat
ten, that's not forbidding me more, I can't eat ten without eating
nine. תשע לא אכל עשרה לא אכיל. tesha lo ochal asara lo
ochil. If you can't eat nine, you can't eat ten. So actually
ironically, if you say ten, it's actually a not a stronger שבועה,
shevuah. not as forbidding more, cause the nine was already forbidden. Okay.
So now he's primed his brother to say the opposite, always overcorrecting.
He's primed his brother to say fine, it's only going to be
one. So now here's the question. שבועה שלא אוכל עשר ותשע מהו?
shvua she-lo ochal eser ve-thesha mahu? So let's say he said 'I
won't eat ten' and then 'I won't eat nine.' So he said,
'Oh, I know the answer, it's only one. אינו חייב אלא אחת.'
eino chayav ella achas. אמר ליה, אשתבישתא, ishtabishata, ah, got you again,
no! In this case, this one
he should have figured out, because
if nine and ten, ten was considered to be not a bigger
scope, ten and nine, if he was just thinking clearly, so nine
does forbid more. עשר הוא דלא אכיל התשע מי אכיל? eser hu
d'lo ochil hatesha mi ochil? When you said ten, you won't eat
ten, but you could eat nine. So the second one that said
nine actually was a more powerful שבועה. shevuah Meaning he ate ten,
he over twice? Exactly. Okay. So anyway, that was hilarious. That was
mean and hilarious. Okay. Anyway. So אמר אביי, amar Abaye, so now
anyway, but that was a little bit—so the חידוש chidush is, I
mean, the ten and the nine isn't the חידוש, chidush, although we
could have easily imagined making the same mistake, having not, you know,
thinking that through, ten is bigger than nine. But the other one
is very important and also, like once you say it, it's obvious,
but, you know, we wouldn't have necessarily thought that first. A past
oriented שבועה, shevuah if you do it multiple times, you're חייב chayav
for every one, cause it's not like one is taking effect on
top of the other, every single שבועה shevuah, is a false שבועה.
shevuah Okay. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, said אביי, Abaye, זימנין דמשכחת לה
להא דאיפא כדאמר. zimnin d'mishkachas lah leha d'Eifa kedemar. There's times that
actually איפא Eifa's last statement would be correct. That actually, if you
said ten and then you said nine, which you would think that
then when you eat ten you transgress both, nine is a, you
know, takes effect in a way that ten doesn't, and then when
you did ten you transgressed both, he says there's times that... There's
actually a way in which if you said ten and then you
said nine, you would only bring one קרבן korban even if you
ate all ten. What would be the case? דאמר רבא D'amar Rava
because רבא says שבועה שלא אוכל תאנים וענבים וחזר ואמר שבועה שלא
אוכל תאנים. Shevuah she'lo ochal te'einim v'anavim v'chazar amar shevuah she'lo ochal
te'einim. A guy said a שבועה shevuah. I won't eat both, not
either, but this means both. There's a whole discussion רש"י Rashi תוספות,
Tosafos I'll read this רש"י's Rashi way. I won't eat both figs
and grapes. So I'm only חייב chayav if let's say I eat
a כזית of figs plus a כזית of grapes. That was my
first שבועה. shevua. And then I say וחזר ואמר שבועה שלא אוכל
תאנים, v'chazar v'amar shevuah she'lo ochal te'einim, just a שבועה I won't
eat figs, a כזית of figs. So that one, that's like the
ten and the nine. That one takes effect because I would transgress
that one even if I just ate the figs. Okay, ואכל תאנים,
v'achal te'einim, and then I went and ate the figs. Boom, that's
קרבן korban number one. והפריש קרבן, V'hifrish korban, and I separated off
a קרבן korban because I did this שבועה בשוגג. b'shogeg. ואחר כך
אכל ענבים, V'achar kach achal anavim, and then I ate the grapes,
לחודיהו, l'chudeihu, just ate grapes. Guess what? You don't bring a קרבן
korban for that. Why? Wouldn't you transgress the grape plus fig שבועה?
No. הוי להו ענבים חצי שיעור וחצי שיעור לא מחייב קרבן. Havei
lehu anavim chatzi shiur v'chatzi shiur lo mechayeiv korban. Once you separated
a קרבן korban out for the figs, the figs sort of became
their whole identity now was the violation of the fig שבועה. The
fact that the קרבן korban is separated means this was a violation
of the first שבועה, here's my קרבן korban for it, and now
somehow it can't combine with something else for another קרבן, korban, it's
already in this box. Okay, somehow that's what's done by separating out
the קרבן. korban. It doesn't allow it to still be relevant to
how we're thinking about this other thing that you did. Okay, הכא
נמי, hacha nami, so I can give you a similar scenario here.
דאמר שבועה שלא אוכל עשרה וחזר ואמר שבועה שלא אוכל תשעה. D'amar
shevuah she'lo ochal asarah v'chazar amar shevuah she'lo ochal tishah. So if
you just ate all ten straight it would be two קרבנות. korbanos.
But if what you did was ואכל תשעה והפריש קרבן ואחר כך
אכל עשירית, v'achal tishah v'hifrish korban v'achar kach achal asiris, you said
nine and then you separated a קרבן korban and then you ate
the tenth, so once you separated a קרבן korban for the nine,
you basically segregated it out. Okay, and now it's only associated with
that first קרבן korban and cannot also be relevant for this other
שבועה and this other קרבן. korban. הוי עשירית חצי שיעור וחצי שיעור
לא מחייב. Havei asiris chatzi shiur v'chatzi shiur lo mechayeiv. So at
least in one scenario איפא Aifa didn't... you didn't trip him up
four times, only tripped him up three times, okay. But that poor
איפא, Aifa, real four or... exactly, poor איפא. Aifa. I will say
one last thing that תוספות Tosafos says, interesting. תוספות Tosafos says that
it might make a difference about as how you said the nine
and the ten and he sort of discusses this with the זיתים
zeitim and the ענבים. anavim. If basically if there's ten things here
and I say any nine I won't eat and then I say
I won't eat all ten, okay, then he says then the second
one doesn't take effect because I would have to eat nine before
I ate the ten. That's what we said. But if I say
specifically I won't eat these nine, so basic... and then I say
I won't eat all ten, because now my שבועה is clearly identifying
one that was left out from the rest of the group, even
though there's no way to transgress it without eating those nine, but
since I'm specifically, you know, including something that had been excluded before
because I said a specific nine, then תוספות Tosafos says that then
is actually considered to be a bigger שבועה. It's a שבועה that
has relevance to this thing in a way that these did not,
and then we would actually say that the ten would take effect
on top of the nine. So that's another way to come ahead
and defend איפא. Aifa. Okay, so that's interesting that תוספות Tosafos sort
of says that, you know, that that would be also with the
זיתים zeitim and ענבים anavim because he had a different גרסא girsa
than רש"י. Rashi. He said first I said I won't eat זיתים,
zeitim, and then I said I won't eat זיתים zeitim plus ענבים.
anavim. Now you should say that that shouldn't take effect, right, because
I can't transgress until I've eaten this and I've already forbidden eating
that. So זיתים וענבים zeitim v'anavim should not take effect on top
of זיתים. zeitim. But תוספות Tosafos says no, in this case it
would actually. Since the שבועה of זיתים zeitim clearly does not include
the ענבים, anavim, so when I take the other one even though
the only way to transgress the other one is by eating something
that's already forbidden, but since the second one forbids a specific object
that is not referred to in the first שבועה, that's considered a
bigger שבועה and it would take effect even though the only way
to get to it is through violating the first שבועה. Would you
say the ענבים anavim was חצי שיעור? chatzi shiur? Yes, that's when
you bring a קרבן korban and break it up. But before... but
if you don't bring a קרבן korban and break it up, okay.
So it's actually interesting according to תוספות Tosafos, there is ways... there's
other ways in which איפא Aifa was correct. Okay, that yes, you
can't transgress without transgressing the first one, but it'll still take effect
if it relates to a specific object not directly referred to in
the original. קרבן korban and break it up, but before, but if
you don't bring a קרבן korban and break it up. Okay, so
it's actually interesting. According to תוספות, there is ways, there's other ways
in which רבא was correct. Okay, that yes, you can't transgress without
transgressing the first one, but it'll still take effect if it relates
to a specific object not directly referred to in the original שבועה.
Okay, we will end here.